we're speaking about sankaras
earlier and
how it's usually translated
well how we were translating it in the
past with determinations
but you seem to be
translating it now as activities
activations yeah
yeah well see the problem with it it's
just as i said before you when you look into
as i said before you when you look into
the suttas there's often
there's often a very practical
instructions given by the buddha how you
know how to like how to calm the
sankaras how to regard them and so on
but any other way it just was not any other
any other way it just was not any other
translation it just wasn't practical
enough how to count determinations but i'll
how to count determinations but i'll
just refrain from determining but what
is it how am i determining things i'm
not determining anything
or even even even more than big use
formations mental formations well
everything is a mental information
everything is just ankara
okay but so what how do i what so under
that same mental level what do i do how
could the suitors talk about it the
buddha gives examples
of comments and cutters
and calming center basically equates
with samadhi
so so like just practically i was
looking practically into it how would
you convey that which sankara's are you
could just say sankaras and every person
knows what sankara that's fine but
if if somebody's still not familiar yeah
it is it is obviously you know sabi
sankara anichi
sabes
so it's an important
important thing
so how can you make it not so abstract
pretty much
and then just look into what's what's in
common to whether it's a mental
formation whether it's a determination
whether it's chaitanya intention because
that's said
uh chair thinners of sight sound smell
test touches that's what sankaras are
the buddhists
so what's in common is that those things
are active
movements intentions intentions
directions pressures
so a form of activity
so it's it's the activities
in the broadest term
being conscious it's the fundamental
cincada that's already a form of activation
that's already a form of activation
like you know wake up
switch your power on you're aware you're
not doing anything
but you are active so that's how fast
sankaras go and that's exactly why
sankara's determined vinayana in patrice
mufada as well
why sankaras
are the cause of vinana to be
established ignorance is caused to
establish sankaras sankara's established
vinana so it's not just i'm not doing anything
so it's not just i'm not doing anything
i'm free from cincadas
abstaining from doing is something
you're doing
so that's your activity
if you can't escape sankatas
by by not having them because you will
be doing that
which is an activity on the basis of you
being conscious and intentional
so stealing of cincadas is a relative
thing if you think you can just do away with
if you think you can just do away with
them well you are on the level of
bodhisattva who thought how do i find
peace by by not doing anything by removing
by by not doing anything by removing
doing of anything and in the end he
wanted to even stop doing the breathing
and he said but this is not this will
kill me but there will be no still
supreme freedom
so then he realized it's not about
removing the activities
it's about removing the particular
aspect of them hence avija ignorance of
that aspect of activities
is the root of all problems not the
activities for which you need to still
and that's exactly what gradual training
is patimok is the first keeping the
virtue restrained by the virtue is the first
restrained by the virtue is the first
basically
layer of reducing the activities of the
unwholesome kind
moderating eating moderating the
activities that you have to do
not distracting yourself with work with
talk with company again moderating
activities that you don't have to do
unless you have to do them
seclusion it's just no no activities of a
it's just no no activities of a
distracting kind
but obviously you still are active in
seclusion you move you talk well maybe
not talk to yourself something but but
you move you move you think you intend
you plan all of that but now those
activities can become more obvious more
discernible because you're in seclusion not
because you're in seclusion not
distracted by coarser activities and
that's exactly the process of stealing
the centers guarding the sense those
the ultimate preventing from sort of
spilling into the unwholesome domain
into the domain of the unwholesome
activities
so the uh
so the whole point there it's not like
i'll just stop doing everything
it's more like just to see the
relationship between wholesome
activities and not going into the
unwholesome activities and then
fundamentally to see that aspect that
you are ignorant of
in regard to the activities they will
free you from
activities and all the suffering
and that aspect
is ownership of the activities
the fundamental activity of taking
things mind
taking things as belonging to me
that's that's also another thing you do
the buddha called it
mind making ahankara i'm making
it's not on the level of i choose to
make this mine it's on the level of
being conscious towards things as if
they're yours so it's very subtle
sankara of course
but if you have been practicing the
gradual training it will be the most
obvious thing
you take things as mine that's what why
you are
not other way around
the activities are there that's why you
have sense of self not other way around
usually it's i am i'm active i'm
inactive i am things are mine or not mine if i
i am things are mine or not mine if i
relinquish them no
things are yours that's already activity
activities are already there you're
already taking them implicitly as to you
for you
thus that's why you have a sense of self
so you don't instill the activities
because the magical piece will happen
will sankara subside no
there is no stealing of activities in
that sense samsara is the fundamental
activity of perpetually active wandering
on
and on and on and it never ends
it doesn't matter what you do unless you
remove the ownership of those neutral
activities that you have discerned on a
kind of withdrawing yourself from every
single unwholesome activity on the body
speech and mind
gradual training
so when that's discerned enough
there is no more sense of i am taking
these things up there is no hankara mama
kara there is no vijaya in regard to
sankara so sankaras are gone
so sankaras are gone
so the activities that are left are the
activities on account of this conscious
body and name and form externally for
another hunt and he knows when that
breaks apart when that exhausts itself
that will be the end of it because the
ownership is so the true stealing the
true samadhi is the removal of that
sense of self in regard to activities to
remove that taking up his mind
to remove that self-sentence being put
first and seeing
and seeing
sankara nicholas
self-centeredness of dhamma
is all not self-centered anymore it's
and that's where the first jhana is the
basis for that complete uprooting of the
sense of self
it's the first basis of the first
non-activity abiding in non-activities a
synonym for jhana
but then the buddha said but when i'm in
jannah when i walk
sit go to toilet
so oh so there are activities in jhana
so what isn't in jhana
well chula veda says imagine what isn't
there sister damadina the nun she she says the
sister damadina the nun she she says the
sense of i am is not there
one one who is in first jana does not
think i am in the first jhana i enter
the first jana i exit the vajana i shall
be this long there is no sense of i am
there is no achenkara being pre-made
that's now there being self-centered
it's just sankatas that from that point
of view of ownership are thoroughly left
alone inactive
and she says she also answered in the
same question she said it's because
one's mind has been developed beforehand
through stilling of that taking things
is mine on the basis of complete virtue
and gradual training and withdrawal and
seclusion the mind enters or the mind basically
the mind enters or the mind basically
abides in a state of not taking things
as i am even on the level of thought so
you have thinking and pondering purified
from ownership
because well then you start seeing that
impersonal the body as an impersonal
that is already exactly the experience
of in the first jana everything is
impersonal top to bottom
whatever you look that's what the buddha
did encourage
he said that the base for our hanship is
the first jana or higher
in the trinket and then he said how is
it so
well for a monk who is in the first
genre if he then regards everything in that
if he then regards everything in that
first jhana as
as perilous as dart everything that's
very wholesome everything not taking
itself regarded in a way that that it's not
regarded in a way that that it's not
wanted then his conscience completely
turns away from any basis and that's a
complete freedom
but you won't be able to so purely
regard things
see them in the nature as dart as that
is not worth having
if you still self-centered if there is
still conceit basically if you're not in
the first gen
so first gianna
talk walking
standing laying down eating going toilet
seclusion active very active
active very active
yet completely abiding in non-activity
of taking things is mine
so it's it's also completely opposite of
any notion of because see people do have
this recognition of stealing the
sankaras you know people read the
suitors how did you steal them well imagine
how did you steal them well imagine
you're walking you ask yourself why am i
walking so fast let me slow down
why don't i stand
why don't i sit down why don't i lay
down so there is this whole kind of
pretty much
infinite layers of how much you still
the activities but not as a goal in
itself and not as as something that will
lead you then to a magical revelation of
the goal
you won't find that in the surface
but most people's techniques and
meditation practices exactly that
activities that they do
with an underlying view that this will
result give me the result
give me the result
and that's the fundamental principle of
the activity of sexuality
i work i earn i protect i gain i enjoy i
engage and i get pleasure as a reward
and there's a suit everybody says what
is the danger well
different sutras were talking about the
dangerous sensuality
what it is but in this particular one it
says the dangerous centrality is here a
man recognizes
oh because i'm attached and dependent
on the pleasure of the senses you know
pleasure of having wife kids everything
else i am i am
burdened
i am basically
i suffer under the pressure of duty for
work earning protecting boring providing
earning protecting boring providing
all those duties are now not optional
for you because of your dependence on
the pleasure that you get on
on account of the census that requires
your engagement on all this high level
of
providing worrying constantly moving to
be there because if you slow down these
things will go away and then immense
suffering will happen because your mind
is dependent on it so he realizes the
danger of depending on the sensuality is
all the all the pressure the work the
burden of all these activities they
become unavoidable then
the only way to avoid them is to remove
your dependence on the pleasure
and that's exactly why you have to have
been withdrawn from that type of
dependence for a long time
before you can even start approaching
the first genre in that true
a sense seeing these activities on the
level that they should be seen
and these neutral activities i'm talking
about it's exactly what we've been
talking about just in different terms in
all these talks you know like finding an
impersonal anchor the body there
underneath your currently emotionally
engaged activity
or this that worry hindrances whatever
else all of that is constantly undermined and
all of that is constantly undermined and
underlined
by
the physicality of the body you know oh
i'm so worried and i'm thinking about
but look all these activities the body
is doing that i'm completely unaware of
or if i'm aware of it i'm putting it
second i'm putting my worry first i am
first what concerns me is first this is second
what concerns me is first this is second
this is irrelevant why would i
then people sometimes might recognize oh
actually no
be mindful of the body
is how you calm your mind
but then they take that mindfulness in
their directly active i am doing the
mindfulness of the body sense
which means that will now be undermined
and underlined by the actual peripheral
physicality of the body we're not seeing
anything would you not think because now
they make it a thing of i am mind doing
this is important for me
and that's where your meditation
practice mindfulness whatever else is
just mechanical observances that's the
only way to see it is as we've been
saying many times is peripherally so
whatever's there you're engaged with
your sense of self with your sense of
ownership peripheral to that you discern
the body you know emitting sounds noises
sweating tired laying positions all
these activities reviewing the organs
the buddha encourages it's the same
purpose it's not a medical examination
or some again mystical release no
peripherally see that while you're so
deeply concerned about something or
related that is the fleshy beating heart skin
that is the fleshy beating heart skin
nose enduring there in this lump
a sack yeah behind everything filled
with various types of beans like the
simulator look at these types of beans
that types of beans
behind everything moving living on its
own not even aware that there is you
such and such they're concerned about
things and whatever you might be
concerned or go for or reject or rejoice
in is second to the physicality of a
you know living operating body subject
to elements
uh and everything else it's second to it
no matter how self-important you are
it's second to the physicality of that
sack of skin
it cannot be otherwise and if you stop
and think about it you realize but the
reason why people don't understand it is
because when they stop and think about
it they over overdo it they make it into
think they don't see it on the right
level which is peripheral level which is
where the level of mindfulness is
the personal activity happening exactly
impersonal activity activities that have
no ahankara and mamankara in level of
activation are there but you don't see the
are there but you don't see the
connection
because you're self-centered and those
are the activities that matter to you so
whether you do your rana panasati or
sati patana
that all these impersonal activities
they could serve as a perfect anchor for
complete removal of ownership and
complete vija of sankar
which would then remove the dependence
on of consciousness on the level of
activity and it will free you from suffering
and it will free you from suffering
and that's why people depend on
activities that's where people are
afraid of solitude and inactivity and so on
of solitude and inactivity and so on
because the conscience depends on a
certain level of engagement engagement
another form of activity another form of
cincada do you want to find the impersonal
do you want to find the impersonal
activities that are occurring
all the time
regardless of of your mental state
hindrance your intentions feelings just
feeling feeling well exactly see
in and out breathing
is activity of the body
neutral activity of the body it's an
activity but activities the buddha said
it does not tire you out
and does not bring unwholesome things to
increase it actually makes them decrease
but it's an activity of the body
so you can engage with it so to learn
how to see it peripherally
as i said before you find your breath
underneath so to speak
thinking and pondering is the activity
the activity of the speech
it's impossible to speak unless thinking
and pondering is active
it's just inconceivable
and fundamentally feeling perception
coming and going arising on its own are
the activities of the heart of chitta
that's what defines chit cheetahs the
activities of that kind so you remove
ignorance ownership of feelings and
perceptions in the broadest sense
your cheetah basically has been freed
so the activities cannot cause you
suffering that's why presence of
activity means presence of dukkha sabe
sankara doesn't matter what doesn't matter how
doesn't matter what doesn't matter how
he finds in kara
the activity of the activity the
activity well yeah exactly
but for somebody who's not free from eye
making in my making every activity
implies i'm making in my making because
that's the fundamental activity based on
a video
you remove a video you remove eye making
and mind making activity from the mind
then you can't say activity is there
that's why the buddha from putin's point
of view arahant sankaras have ceased
because for petunia's point of view
there is no other type of sankara that
is not rooted in
if it were exactly you would be at least
a sort of runner
but yes arahant still
talks walks
perceives does things by body by speech by mind
does things by body by speech by mind
yet there are no synchros so relatively
speaking there are no synchros so yes
that's why like
i was considering translating sankaras
as activities
activity slash activation i suppose but
you do want to have that
emphasis on that it's it's not a random
activity of a rolling stone or something
it's the activities that are based on
intentional action because intention is
another form of activity
it's the fundamental activity
in practically speaking
every consciousness is intentional
it's not a separate thing
and when would have said what are the
determinations he said it's the
intentions of sight sound what is the
aggregate of determinations he said is
the intentions of sight sound smell
taste touches that's the aggregate of
activities that's the aggregate of cincadas
that's the aggregate of cincadas
that's the aggregate of determinations
which are very translated
so sankaras are the intentions of sight
sound smell taste touches
the activations of satsang smell taste
touches the intentions of your senses
sorry you well they are actually the
intentions of your senses but for a mind
it's not free from a vega
mind making eye making is what's first
which means even when these intentions
come you have not created them they are
yours and that's where people are by
default moved by what they see here smell this
moved by what they see here smell this
touch
and immediately assume the ownership and
immediately assume engagement so that's
why again the the gradual training
withdrawal from that you still have eye
making and mind making and so on
but you are withdrawing from that
automatic kind of assumption and action
out of assumed ownership the word
science and smell test touches
so that you get to see then if you're
withdrawn sufficiently enough you get to
see that
i'm making and my making as ah that's
the stop doing that
stop doing that
everything else is fine can be left
alone like a tree stump killed at the
root you start you're seeing the creature
you start you're seeing the creature
you start seeing creature exactly and
that's what that nun said tomorrow when
he was talking about what are you doing
who are you talking who referring to
there is only sankara's manifesting and
enduring basically
in other words she's not even seeing any
of these activities even as a as a
coarser form of self so there's like
some probably some traces of conceit she
must have been on a gummy or or you know
very close to other hundred so there's
just sankara's coming and going
just activities manifesting and then new
activities manifesting itself
but it's important to not fall into view
well it's important actually to step
outside of the view because most people
abide in that view
whereby you you think they're okay so i
just stop everything and that's how i
stop that's another activity
choosing to abstain from choice
choosing to not intend this or that is
what you're intending right there and
then abstaining from these particular
choices is my choice
so that's why there is no you can't
remove the sankatas
as in to make them not be there and you
cannot possibly act your way out of
action so the camera could come a bad camera
so the camera could come a bad camera
sure but kama's always going to be there
unless you remove that ownership on the
fundamental level of intention and
consciousness and your thought
you can't yeah you can't decide you
can't decide that because that's that's
a very very strong very close form of
activity
like you can something's moving really
fast i don't know get this so my my hands are
i don't know get this so my my hands are
very active my hands are very active okay
okay
so now i still the movement but this is
now my activity
yes so it's it's a relative stillness in
regards to doing this with these leaves
relative stillness but it's still an
activity because if i stop holding onto
the leaf it's going to start moving
again so don't have the view to expect that
so don't have the view to expect that
you just rigidly stop everything and
that's how you enter the piece of
non-activity because that's going to be
your activity and whoever committed to
those intense sort of
focusing controlling meditation
techniques well if they're self-honest
they would see that
initially they got the peace from that
relative stealing and after a while all
they were getting is frustration and
trying to get that piece back and they
were getting more wound up and more
intense and i know from my own
experience while i'm still a layman you know you
while i'm still a layman you know you
try everything you don't know what's
right or wrong and yeah you start doing
this technique and then you two days
three days and then just
oh the peace is gone because now this is
your reality
stop everything stop everything i will
move slowly i will not speak i'll never
speak i'll never look at anything
and that becomes very active thing that
you're engaged with
so there's no peace
so the peace is true piece of stealing
sankaras is the piece of
is the piece of
removing the ownership so the true piece
of meditation that still this encoders
correctly is the removal of the
ownership of cincadas not removal of
cincadas that's why for the correct
meditation you need the right view you
need to understand where the problem is
the ownership you can't just do it
because you're doing it with ahankara
and mamakar